

ROBOTICS AND MACHINE LEARNING RESEARCHER

Via Della Libertà, 15-B, 16129 Genoa, Italy

🛘 (+39) 391 165 43 70 | 🗷 domingo.esteban@iit.it | 🌴 www.domingoesteban.com | 🖸 domingoesteban | 🗖 domingoesteban

Summary

PhD candidate and research fellow in Advanced and Humanoid Robotics; with an M.Sc. in Robotics and Automation, a B.Sc. in Industrial Engineering and a B.Sc. in Economics and Business.

Carrying out the doctoral research activities in the Department of Advanced Robotics at the Italian Institute of Technology (IIT). The goal of my PhD program is to endow robots with the ability to autonomously acquire motor skills through a better use of the data obtained from its interaction with the world. My research is mainly supported by the design and application of (deep) reinforcement learning, optimal control and supervised/unsupervised learning techniques.

I have research experience both in academia and industry in machine learning, robot control and robot simulation.

Research Interests

Robot Reinforcement Learning

Model-free and model-based algorithms that scale to robotics problems (high-dimensional, continuous states and actions, hierarchical and multi-task problems)

Optimal Control Control with learned models, control with inaccurate models, Stochastic Optimal Control, MPC

Humanoids Whole-body motions with various tasks, multi-contact motion, locomotion, manipulation

Imitation Learning Inverse reinforcement learning, shared human-robot representations, behavioral cloning

Education

Istituto Italiano di Tecnologia (IIT) – Università degli Studi di Genova

PHD IN BIOENGINEERING AND ROBOTICS - CURRICULUM: ADVANCED AND HUMANOID ROBOTICS

Nov. 2015 - Exp. July 2019

Universidad Carlos III de Madrid

M.Sc. IN ROBOTICS AND AUTOMATION

Universidad Nacional de San Agustín de Arequipa

B.Sc. in Industrial Engineering

Universidad Católica San Pablo

B.Sc. IN ECONOMICS AND BUSINESS

Sept. 2012 - July 2014

Genoa, Italy

Madrid, Spain

Arequipa, Peru

Apr. 2004 - Apr. 2009

Arequipa, Peru

Mar. 2006 - Dec. 2010

Publications

2019 Esteban, D.; Rozo, L.; Caldwell, D. "Hierarchical reinforcement learning for concurrent discovery of compound and composable policies", IEEE/RSJ International Conference on Intelligent Robots and Systems (IROS) – (Accepted)

Esteban, D.; Rozo, L.; Caldwell, D. "Learning Deep Robot Controllers by Exploiting Successful and Failed Executions", IEEE-RAS International Conference on Humanoid Robots (Humanoids)

Delhaisse, B.*; **Esteban, D.***; Rozo, L.; Caldwell, D. "*Transfer Learning of Shared Latent Spaces between Robots with Similar Kinematic Structure*", IEEE International Joint Conference on Neural Networks (IJCNN) – (* Equal contribution)

Martínez, S.; **Esteban, D.**; Jardón-Huete, A.; Balaguer, C. *"Anticipative Humanoid Postural Control System for Locomotive Tasks"*, IEEE-RAS International Conference on Humanoid Robots (Humanoids)

Skills

Machine Learning SW PyTorch, TensorFlow, OpenAl-Gym, scikit-learn, GPy

Robotics SW ROS, YARP, Gazebo, MuJoCo, PyBullet, RobotStudio, OpenCV **Programming** Python, C, C++, MATLAB®/Octave, Shell scripting, HTML/CSS

Languages English, Spanish, Italian

Experience

Department of Advanced Robotics (ADVR) - Istituto Italiano di Tecnologia (IIT)

Genoa, Italy

AFFILIATED RESEARCHER Nov. 2015 - PRESENT

- · Member of the Learning and Interaction group.
- Research focused on robot learning in humanoid robots:
 - (Deep) reinforcement learning for continuous control tasks: Soft Actor Critic (SAC), Guided Policy Search (GPS), Deep Deterministic Policy Gradients (DDPG), Proximal Policy Optimization (PPO), Normalized Advantage Functions (NAF), REPS, PILCO, PI2.
 - Hierarchical and multi-task reinforcement learning in robotics.
 - Exploiting failed executions to improve efficiency and safe-exploration in Reinforcement Learning of robotics tasks.
 - Transfer learning of skills between humanoid robots.
 - Behavioral cloning of whole-body movements

IXION Industry and Aerospace

Madrid, Spain

ROBOTICS ENGINEER June 2013 - Oct. 2015

- Design, programming and implementation of locomotion, perception, localization, SLAM and motion planning algorithms for the autonomous
 robots of the company: unmanned multi-rotors vehicles (UAS), unmanned ground vehicles (UGV) and autonomous underwater vehicles (AUV),
 in ROS.
- · Simulation of autonomous mobile robots.
- Programming of navigation algorithms for autopilot systems in real-time embedded systems.
- Programming and implementation of Hardware-in-the-loop (HIL) simulation systems for the navigation of autonomous robots.
- Development and wrapping of sensor drivers in real-time embedded systems.

Universidad Carlos III de Madrid

Madrid, Spain

ROBOTICSLAB - HUMANOIDS GROUP RESEARCH COLLABORATOR

Mar. 2013 - July 2015

- Design, programming and implementation of whole-body trajectory generation algorithms for TEO, the full-size humanoid robot of the Humanoids group.
- Simulation of a humanoid robot in Gazebo simulator.
- Design and development of ROS nodes in C++ and Python.
- · Development of a MATLAB® graphical user interface (GUI) for the generation of whole-body trajectories for TEO humanoid robot.
- Development of shell scripts for GNU/Linux Operating Systems.

Barrick Gold Corporation - Minera Barrick Misquichilca S.A.

Huaraz, Peru Jan 2011 - Dec 2011

Intern

- Data analysis and use of data mining techniques to obtain information from the databases of the company.
- Employee personal data update and generation of reports in Oracle R12 System.
- Statistics, indicators and documentation update of the Human Resources Quality Management System according to ISO 9001 standard.

Professional Development

Deep Learning and Bayesian Methods

Moscow, Russia

DEEP|BAYES, SAMSUNG RESEARCH, NATIONAL RESEARCH UNIVERSITY HIGHER SCHOOL OF ECONOMICS (HSE)

August 2018

An Introduction to Spatial (6D) Vectors and their use in Robot Dynamics

Genoa, Italy
March 2017

ISTITUTO ITALIANO DI TECNOLOGIA

Robot Programming

Genoa, Italy

ISTITUTO ITALIANO DI TECNOLOGIA

July 2016

REGML: Regularization Methods for Machine Learning

Genoa, Italy
June 2016

Università degli Studi di Genova

34116 2010

Machine Learning: A computational Intelligence Approach

Genoa, Italy
June 2016

Università degli Studi di Genova

Control of Mobile Robots
GEORGIA INSTITUTE OF TECHNOLOGY

Mar. 2014

Autonomous Mobile Robots - AMRx

edX (MOOC)

ETH ZURICH (ETHX)

Feb 2014

Machine Learning

Coursera (MOOC)

Coursera (MOOC)

STANDFORD UNIVERSITY

July 2013